We now dive into the Lorawan network infrastructure.
First on the left, this diagram represents the Lorawan, end devices. End devices don't specifically
transmit to the gateway, but they transmit to all gateways present in the coverage area.
Gateways will be responsible of the transmission between on one side, the lora modulation and on
the other side the IP network,
so basically Internet. To be understood by the network server and the application server, the LoRaWAN
frame arriving from the end device must contain not only the user payload but also all input and data for
keeping the transmission secured.
These two servers have very specific rules and will see them later in detail in another video.
So the structure of the overall Lorawan network is quite simple and stops here.
This means that once a data is stored in the application server, the Lorawan protocol doesn't apply
anymore.
So everything that happened on the right side of the diagram has nothing to do with LoRaWAN.
Here, on the left we have the Lorawan protocol, and here on the right we have the usual WEB protocols.
These protocols will be used to export the user data from the application server into, for example,
an IoT platform or any cloud services to compute the data and probably at the end make them available
to the end user.
So how can we export the user payload ? That would be done mainly using two protocols which are HTTP and
MQTT.
But once again, that has nothing to do with Lorawan. For the end user.
The only thing that interests him is to see is data on chart table nicely represented in a web page,
so he doesn't want to have anything to do with the Lorawan server.
So that's why there are two steps : one dealing only with the Lorawan protocol and the other one with
the user services.
In the following video will first see the role of the network server and the applications server.
Then in a second time will have a look at the gateways and finally will go on the end device side and explain
the different classes A, B, and C.
Later, in another chapter, we'll also see how we manage to export data using HTTP or MQTT.
So the payload sends by the end device will be available to the user.